welcome to the solution racing we just
decided before
starting recording that we are doing it
on food security
as eric would you like to start since
you uh suggested the topic and
my guess is you know a little bit about
this these two billion people that are
going to
not be food secure well i don't i i only
know it as a number i mean
it was a thing i read i mean i would
imagine you've both heard about the
pesticide failure to deliver pesticides
back in january which led to which has
led to the locust plague in uh asia and
africa right and
it is for this reason among others that
as many as two billion people will not
be producing enough food for themselves
this year and so
yeah i mean the consequences of that god
knows i mean that's a mess the likes of
which we have
never seen before right um
so yeah god bless kobe god bless kobet
and our excessive ridiculous
response to it god bless you all
all right i can definitely share even
though i actually didn't know about the
i knew about the locust but i didn't
know it was because pesticides weren't
for all i know we could have kept
putting pesticides on and their cell
would be locus because of how pesticides
and pests
work but um yes when kobit first
happened my first thought was for our
food security i'm like i'm gonna grow my
own garden not of course realizing that
i'm never gonna have food insecurity
there's always gonna yes my
my brand might not be available i went
and tried to buy annie's mac and cheese
because it's what my kid will eat
and it's way better than the
alternatives it's like that's my food
insecurity right like annie's mac and
cheese isn't available so i have to buy
the generic stuff or craft dinner
and the the
that we demote agricultural workers
to the base of society and are like we
don't even pay the minimum wage in
canada we bring them
in from generally mexico and they get
our benefits like our medical benefits
and such and even ei
but they don't get a minimum wage and
then they're hosed but we didn't do that
this year because of covid
and so even in the west where
we have our own food right we're growing
it here
we're not it's rotting it's rotting in
the fields because there aren't enough
agricultural workers and then people who
are working in rice fields working be
doing assistance farming but on them not
i guess not assistance for me but more
wide scale are like stop and go home so
it's like the places that are developing
that have
like they're gonna end up selling their
food to us it's gonna be quinoa it's
gonna be like we get our food because we
can pay higher prices
but unless you have an actual garden
that you can eat out of
you're not gonna be able to get food in
your marketplace and so i could see
that billions of people were about to
starve and i grew my own little garden
thinking that you know what i mean
there's gonna be a roaming anarchist
i don't know something and at least
there's some calories added to it
but yeah this is a massive
issue we need to eat and yet the same
the positive side of what's currently
happening in my own life not in the
world
is like i just made zucchini pasta the
other night from a zucchini that i grew
and i'm not really a big gardener
but like the weird
like gardening is so beautiful you grow
it
seeds come out so you can like i grew
you know what i mean i had baby zucchini
plants that i bought as babies
and then now i have unlimited seeds or i
can just take the seeds out and plant
them next year theoretically we'll see
if it works unless they're terminator
seeds
that like one zucchini gives me enough
seeds to grow enough zucchinis for my
entire block which would give us enough
seeds to grow
you know for the entire city and yet
because we kind of have demoted
growing our own food to the base level
it's like oh that's beneath me i'll just
buy it in the supermarket
but you don't have food security unless
you can grow your own food and
all over the world people can't grow
their own food because of pesticides
because of herbicides because of
there isn't enough fertilizer and
there's not enough land they don't have
access to it
yeah this is a huge problem so thanks
for suggesting it i hope we come up with
something
matt would you like to share for this
portion of what it currently looks like
yeah sure um i think you brought up a
couple of interesting things
um about you know i heard back when kind
of covid first
struck all of these uh dairy farms and
um you know cow processing meat
processing plants they had to just like
throw away all of this perfectly good
milk and
slaughter all of these innocent animals
like
why because supply chain issues or
just like like the problem wasn't we
didn't have enough food
it was just like the system that was
built up around the supply chains and
and the workers and all of that broke
down
and so and then you know compounding
that with
i don't know if you guys went through
the whole uh toilet paper
epidemic um earlier in the year but
that that was a little scary not just
because of toilet paper
but because it showed i think the
fragility
in the existing system meaning
that you could go to a store and
there could be enough toilet paper for
everybody but just because of
you know hoarding and greed and and
supply chain shocks you know it would
just be
completely sold out um and i think
you're seeing that all across the board
i mean like you go into
uh supplement stores or health food
stores and you try to go buy
zinc or vitamin d3 and
those are just wiped off the shelves
because people are starting to
get the message that nutrition and
supplementation is important
so yeah i think um
it's it's very fragile and then i think
um
one i'm trying to pull this this uh data
point
up here um this is kind of related to
food
but i think what it what it shows is um
the kind of overall uh economic
conditions of at least americans
right now and it says uh roughly
10 to 14 million u.s renter households
that's around 24 million people were
behind on their rent
in september that amounts to 12 to 17
billion dollars in unpaid rent that
figure is expected to rise to 34 billion
in past due rent by january lifting the
moratorium on evictions and foreclosures
will mean that millions of families will
be tossed out on the streets
so i would imagine if you can't pay your
rent
buying food is also going to be a factor
in in your in your life so i think that
is a kind of a compounding factor as
well
so yeah i'll shut up now now we can open
up the discussion
just going just going back to the um
fragility of supply chains thing i mean
it is it's this whole just-in-time thing
right in the name of efficiency
they deliver just what they're going to
need for the next 24 hours until the
next delivery truck arrives yeah and
and one interruption anywhere in that
multi-linked chain
and and the whole thing collapses and
going back to what you were saying
jubilee about the only way
to have food security is to grow your
own food i mean i think there is
some truth to that however as someone
who does grow the majority of my own
food i know how easy it is to up
right and i look at
things that my neighbors grow and things
that are available in the market and
stuff like that and i compare it to my
own produce and
you know what i mean i'm not going but
the stuff i'm going is not nearly as
good it's not nearly as
big or or not always some of it is but i
mean there are many many instances where
what i'm doing is not nearly as good as
what other people are growing right so
other people
you know people have a knack for growing
things or expertise or knowledge built
up over time or
you know handed down through family or
whatever and so
you know i mean what we have right now
is is
it's gone way too far in this direction
where i mean i i'm pulling numbers out
of the air i don't know these to be true
numbers but probably something like 90
of the world's food is produced by you
know maybe 20 or 30
enormous companies right around the
world who who are responsible
and the rest is sort of little niche
suppliers um
and so i think what to long-term food
security
i think starts in school right where
every single school has
a little farm or whatever attached to it
where they grow things and keep
livestock and
every single child as part of their
education is involved in
you know the preparation of the land and
the planting of the seeds and the
tending and the weeding and the
harvesting
and the preparing and the cooking and
the serving and the cleaning up
afterwards
and all of this stuff is integrated into
their school routine
and another really important point i
think you made jubilee is about how
people who are involved in agriculture
are kind of they're very much working
class right they're sort of down at the
bottom of the socio-economic ladders
certainly the farm workers maybe not so
much
the land owners but certainly the farm
workers are right down at the very
bottom and
somehow elevating that right and and and
you know this is an essential thing
there are a few things more essential
than food right and so those that
produce our food for us and it's not to
say that everyone can't do a little bit
right
but broadly speaking there's going to be
in any community there's going to be a
handful of people who
like growing food or into it know about
it are good at it you know what i mean
and and it's right that we rely on them
but building in resilience at local
levels where the
vast majority of food production apart
from specialized diets like bananas
right
bananas you can only grow in tropical
climates if you want bananas in canada
you have no option but to but to
transport them right or build huge
greenhouses whatever but
for the most part 90 95 percent of food
production could be done
within say i don't know a 50 mile radius
right of any of
any given point and and that's so yeah
the three-pronged approach right one
introducing in schools as a really big
part of the school day
right that an hour or two of every
school day is somehow involved in this
you know in this process of production
of food um elevating the status in
society so that it's honored and paid
properly right and um yeah localization
really key in on localization of as much
production as possible both at an
individual level in your gardens
and at a community level in a couple of
fields nearby and that you know
that that sort of thing yeah i just want
to bring up
it's interesting you brought up the
localization because um
so i live in utah and uh utah
as you may know it's uh mormon central
up here and you know say what you want
about the mormons but
they are they they do kind of have a uh
the standards of uh you know resilience
and self-sufficiency and and uh
specifically where i am in my town and
kind of the neighboring towns
um they have like uh maybe about 20
miles away from me there's a huge
um it's like a from the outside it looks
like a big
indoor like football stadium
but it's all filled with um like
agricultural
production um and the reason they do
that is because in the winter they can
continue to grow crops and
in my local town there's lots of
greenhouses
lots of farms cattle
you can tell people just in recent
months have been kind of converting
their existing farms over into
you know growing new crops new products
things like that
and so yeah i think where i am is it's
kind of an interesting case study
in in like like when i think of um
some kind of uh you know
shock to the system and i think to
myself oh well
are we gonna be okay here and you know
i think it'll be scary but i i think we
might be okay here i
just the the level of of production and
ingenuity i see around me is it's it's
very impressive
can you announce a screenshot for a
second i just want to show you guys
something can you allow me to screen
share for a second
yeah yeah go ahead well eric's doing
that matt do you know if
um mormons stock up on guns
oh yeah they love their guns they love
them
i was like i was like i don't know i was
gonna come take the food but you're
right utah might be the one place where
people don't like i almost want a map of
all the mormons
in in wherever i'm wanting to be like i
know where they stocked up on food
because they do they have like a year's
supply
or i don't remember how much yeah
they're two-year two it's it's counseled
by by the mormon church to have like
a two-year supply of food storage so
the individual people up here are pretty
well stocked
um there's a lot of
food forget for your 12 children like
mormon families are also really big
some of them yeah and the home the homes
up here are very
you know they're very large homes and
you know they have like
basements with cold storage that they're
being grained
and this and that and and what's funny
though just about the guns i i was at
yeah it was in a parking lot the other
day of of uh
walmart and somebody had
a truck and on the back of the truck
there was a flag
it was an american flag but instead of
instead of the stripes on the american
flag they were like
uh automatic weapons
so it was like you can tell where that
person
where that person lies yeah that sounds
about i'm just wondering because yeah if
you have food but you don't have guns
then it's hard to
save it can you just allow me just to
allow screen share for me oh yeah did i
not already
sorry i thought you were just getting it
ready more no i'm i'm ready
i was already ready all right i made you
co-host oh wait do you want yes
okay yeah cool
that is a indoor vertical hydroponic
farm
and i mean you can build these things up
basically as high as you want right so
with minimal square foot energy is
obviously the problem here right
they take they take a large amount of
energy but water
nutrients uh all of that kind of stuff
way less than
than growing in soil um but yeah you you
need to provide light obviously
i mean there are versions of these where
you have a rotating building right where
you don't use artificial like use
natural light
and you have a rotating building and so
you're all four sides get exposed to the
sun
during the course of the day i mean i
don't know what the rotation rate is but
every 15 minutes or something
it rotates and so it just it just uses
sunlight
um so yeah i mean this is this seems to
me to be the way to
very quickly i mean obviously there's a
lot of investment involved right but
you know assuming that you're willing to
channel the resources to it this is
something that could be
very very quickly done and could produce
very large amounts of food in urban
environments right
massively reducing the amount of
transportation other agricultural land
that's needed land can then be
allowed to re-wild and blah blah blah i
mean this strikes me as long as you can
figure out a way
to produce the energy this strikes me as
yeah really important part of the way
forward especially in places where we
have cold so much of the year
and places that have a lot of sunlight
but still cold can get solar
um i did want to mention um something
that was during this section we're about
to switch over to the next although i
think we've done some of that part
um this idea of charity versus
solidarity
and i think our our charity model of
food has been around for so long
that it is going to f us over on a grand
scale like
watching what's happening with kovid
where all of these people
were super generous when it first
started but now that we're eight months
in people like wait you asked for
red last month like why can't you get
your together in time it's like
right there's still a pandemic going on
they were in poverty before it ever
began
that there becomes like when you have
access
you want to help people but then there's
too many people to help and you can't
you can't help them all so you end up
becoming like more of a horde like more
well i mean i get my
i'm entitled to this right i worked for
it it's mine
which is fine but we like
being under the poverty line you can't
afford both food and shelter
and so the food portion of that has been
taken over by charity
which means that the government pays you
less and less to offset that
so you're expected to go to the food
bank you're expected to go to soup
kitchens and do those things whereas
that's going to become there's more and
more demand for it
and less and less supply for it and
regular people who never would have done
that are going to need it
and we're seeing it not just in our own
localized version but also globally and
next week when we talk about refugees
the same thing like
we want to be able to take people in but
there becomes a limit and we can't you
know what i mean like you can't
our global supply food chain can't be
based on charity and yet we all
could grow food right we could be
spending four to 10 hours a week in
fields if we didn't think of it as a
lower class
thing just to volunteer
yeah and if we grew up doing it and
loved it you know what i mean yeah
exactly exactly and and to say well
where you know what is our diet
and how do we get it and how do we how
do we do it together instead of okay if
these people are poor they need to be
given stuff
and these people are rich they get
access to everything like how can
without that
how much labor do we have to give how
much resources do we currently have and
can we feed ourselves with that
and can we anyway just that we're about
to see a big
cost of our charity model because we
don't have enough
surplus to give to charity while we're
also figuring out our own
and feeding the world and the world is
about to starve because
they followed yeah everyone has to go
home well those were our agricultural
workers
that's where the charities are so flawed
in the sense that all that charity ever
provides is the bare minimum for
survival to keep you alive right it's
not actually elevating you to
you know um yeah nutrition
but yeah yeah exactly nutrition also
when you go to the food bank nutrition's
not their highest priority and of course
if you're going to get produce it's
going to be potatoes and carrots it's
not going to be you know i mean kale
and things with it with high high
nutrient density and what most of it's
packaged right most of it is stuff that
can sit on a shelf for a while
and in a pandemic what we want is people
with high high high nutrition
right so that they're not as it's like
that's hurt immunity that's the actual
like if you're less like if you're
easier able to fight it off and less
likely to pass it on because you have
proper nutrition in your body
that's what we want globally and yet
we're going to see the opposite happen
and um yeah so we are 20 minutes in we
could probably switch over
like i said we've been very here just
just one more thought on this which
you've kind of already said but just
just just to reaffirm it i mean
you know for for people like us this is
all right you know it means not that big
a deal it's an inconvenience
is all it actually is but for people who
are actually poor i mean i you know
it's important it's impossible for us to
actually understand it i mean i
understand it
at an intellectual level right but i
don't understand it in the sense that i
can
really put myself into feeling that
experience and you know
i mean as is always the case it's the
poor people who are least
able to look after themselves who bear
the
biggest brunt of the of of the
um problems so yeah yeah just i just
work
one more thing i want to add this
section which is very much in this
section
when you talk about the just enough just
in time supply chain right and how
there's no room for growth
and we've talked about this before that
that's also our entire political and
economic system is based on people who
have
low risk tolerance who are like we'll
deal with the chaos as it comes right oh
no the pandemic's not a problem even
though i do about it until it's
exponentially the hospitals are full now
we should start dealing with it
the people who can see four steps out or
can just
you know do exponential math aren't
listened to because we're looked at as
as
like chicken little the sky is falling
and so it's you know i mean
when my first thoughts in march were
like we need to figure out food security
in vancouver in the world and
no one's gonna listen to me right i mean
no one's gonna listen to him but
anything but especially
it's like oh no what we need is people
to stay home for a month right and we
need food
like this isn't if we didn't there's a
reason we have supermarkets as essential
workers
we also need agricultural workers as
essential workers in canada for not
bringing in
in people from mexico we need to
incentivize our own people we need to
have and so this is probably i'll switch
over to the next part
which is what i would like to have seen
happen during this which is a little
weird because it's not
like right now if i could have my ideal
version of a pandemic or let's say we
did need to lock ourselves down because
the virus was deadly enough whether you
believe that or not we needed to take
the economic action to offset the health
one
i would have liked to see in place uh
systems of farmers being able to say
hey food's rotting in my fields i need
people to come and do this if you can
come and take the food you can have it
or you know what i mean come in and
collect it for other people that we can
more easily share where the food is is
getting wasted
and and offset at other places and say
okay like there's a bunch of potatoes
being buried okay well
could we wait a few months could we see
because potatoes are pretty good at
lasting a long time can we see if we're
going to need that and we need to ship
it somewhere else
having a more um global system of when
there's a famine when there's
when there's locus when there's
something else going on that we have a
way to get them food in 3d farms
in greenhouse which isn't necessarily
going to hurt their local
food supply it's actually going to help
them build it and help them work
together to say hey how much do
we need to put in because let's be
honest they're not going to have
the capital but the western world has
the capital and we should be
helping people who we've over
royally in centuries past
that there's ways that anyone can say
we're not food secure as an individual
as a group as a village and
be helped with the tools of like hey
have you thought of 3d farming would
this work in your climate
in your culture with this what what can
you grow in a way to to
to assess that supply chain the
complexity of that supply chain who's
growing it where is it going to
and when it breaks down how do we take
how do we take it up so that it's like
okay well if the potatoes are just
rotting in the field how do we get them
out of the field
where can they go and figuring out how
you get from point a to point b and get
people fed and get calories
in us while also having that resilience
of putting it in the education system
because this is resilience be able to
grow your own food
means that other people can't control
you anywhere near the amount right when
you're starving it's a lot easier to
control you
and if people don't have access to how
to build
build how to grow vegetables like the
planet does it for you it is the only
passive income it is the only thing that
is actually going to exponentially grow
while you're sleeping
is a garden under permaculture and we
can do it with less and less labor
we need access to land and access to
community and and i wish we had
had what i think we will have in place
in five years
five years ago so it was in place now
for for this pandemic
one thing that i want to kind of mention
here is
you know a lot of these things we're
talking about we make the assumption
that we have money or we will have money
or the west is rich
or something like that um but
so what i do for my job is i'm i'm an
investment analyst at a
at a hedge fund and and so i research
this kind of
you know economic data all day
and um things might get
rough out there and so i think when
we're trying to think of solutions
um it might be within our best interest
to think of solutions
that involve maybe us not having as much
money
as we once did i think a lot of people
that are currently
fortunate you know as we get deeper into
this
transition phase that we're experiencing
in the world
um you know that may not be the case
where you know the the once rich people
uh that that might start shifting um
so anyway i just wanted to throw that in
there yeah that was what i was trying to
get to this charity solidarity is we're
gonna have less capacity what is your
beautiful
future look like matt what does food
security look like to you in your life
in the world
in an ideal world
well you know i've always been pretty
health conscious
and and
i think i think we have the answer i
mean i think
i think going local just
hyper hyper local you know grow as much
as you can yourself
and in your hyper local community there
might be somebody out there
that has a much higher growing capacity
than you do
and you know we already kind of live in
cultures where
farmers markets are are a thing
and i think if we increase
that trend i think i think we might be
okay
you know if we just kind of go back to
how we used to do things
and plus we'd all be healthy we'd all be
much healthier if we did that
eric do you want to share you already
shared yeah i was just going to say i
would i would like to see
pretty much the complete elimination of
manufactured foods right of packaged
foods basically i'd like to see the
complete elimination of that
i would like to see people preparing
their own food at home not buying frozen
or dried or whatever in the
supermarket and just boiling it up or
microwaving it or whatever when they get
home
and this is all going to come from what
i said before right there you instill
this
at the level of children uh you know and
after a couple of generations it just
becomes it just becomes completely
normal you know what i mean the idea of
buying a pack of macaroni cheese and
don't get me wrong i love those packets
of macaroni and cheese too i'm not
judging you but i'm just saying the idea
of dining on a packet of macaroni cheese
would become
you know like become an absurdity right
when you've got why would you eat that
when you've got you know
freshly made pasta the guy next door
makes beautiful freshly made pasta and
distributes it around the neighborhood
you know
and so why on earth would you do you
know what i mean the
whole need for all that and the quality
of nutrition that would be obtained by
people from eating
locally grown seasonal freshly done you
know what i mean food as opposed to
stuff that has grown on the other side
of the world picked early stuck in a
freezer
container shipped three quarters of the
way around the world you know what i
mean and and
and all of this kind of thing and the
reduction in pesticides the return to
permaculture right i mean
we have all but murdered the soil i mean
douglas rushkoff talks about this we've
got 40 years left
of topsoil there's 40 harvests left in
the topsoil and then it's dead
we with the the the chemicals the
pesticides the fertilizers the
roundup you know all of this that
we've been plowing into the soil has
destroyed
the mycedial network destroyed the soil
microbiota
uh to the point where it's not going to
be producing in another 40 years
time you know and so
we are right at the very very very end
and unless
you mentioned before controlled jubilee
and i do fear
huge organizations like monsanto for
example you know i mean they they they
grow these seeds they patent them they
sell them to farmers farmers have to buy
new seeds every year they can't they are
terminating seeds right so you can't and
even if you do
you're not allowed to you get sued there
are thousands of farmers
in india who commit suicide because they
can't cope with their lives anymore
because of the financial burdens placed
on them by these
by these um seed manufacturers and and
you know the the
so the idea of control
through food i think is very very
very real which is why there aren't
already vertical farms in every
city in the world right because that
would create
food independence and food independence
means a huge
our lever of control is gone for the
monster
and the monster doesn't relinquish
levers of control and so
yeah can i bring up just one point real
quick
can can we live in a world with
monsanto i mean like
are they gonna turn from the dark side
to the light side
is that being too optimistic or not i
mean
they are the dark side that's the whole
point is that i mean that's the whole
thing
but but how so so if we can't live in a
world with monsanto then
what's to be done with them how do we uh
have them how do we have them exit stage
left here
how do we get them out of the picture no
i don't think you do stop feeding them i
think you make them irrelevant you stop
feeding them exactly right you stop
feeding them you grow
you do what we've been talking about you
figure out ways to do it yourself so
that you don't need them you can still
get
heritage seeds right which do produce
plants which produce seeds which you can
then replant the next year right you can
still get them
now how long that's going to be the case
i do not know i was one of the first
things i did when i moved out here was i
bought
you know like sealed packs these are
like um you know
apocalypse packs of seeds you know
they're good for 50 years or whatever in
the sealed in the sealed bag
um and i've been using those and keeping
seeds from those and so on but
you know i mean there's there's there's
way more to this the chemtrails which
i've now been admitted to right this is
no longer conspiracy theory government
agencies now admit
to the fact that they're putting these
things into the atmosphere in order to
reflect sunlight in order to reduce
the greenhouse effect right but these
chemtrails contain heavy metal
oxides which gradually gradually
gradually sift down into the soil and
poison the soil as well right so even
people who are
tilling their land responsibly and
cycling
crops and leaving to life fallow and
using ruminants and all of this kind of
even people who are doing that are still
having their soils poisoned by
the particulates dropping down from the
atmosphere
so it's it's a it's a very very very
difficult fight to win this one very
different yeah but
like so like daniel schmucktenberger
talks a lot about
you know people with um exponential tech
and and i would include monsanto in
there with
you know the the ability to you know
exponentially
cause way more devastation than we could
have caused in the past
and also exponential in terms of capital
i mean
they they will they will send their
teams of lobbyists to enact laws to
prevent
people like you and i to to
to do what we want to do um
you know like how how do we
you know how do we go up against the
empire like that
you know the i mean
yeah how do you feel the rebel alliance
is what you're asking yeah
we have many many an option i say we
switch over to what we could do with ten
thousand people and a hundred thousand
dollars and there's like a million
options we could get rid of monsanto or
at least get create the
information that would eventually get
rid of them with ten thousand people
under a thousand dollars
we could focus on soil health and
permaculture and like right what is your
soil and how do you improve it
because our topsoil is eroding but we
also have
innovations that help us rejuvenate soil
and rejuvenate ecosystems that weren't
there 10 20 years ago
that are you know what i mean like
biochar and stuff that actually puts it
back in and gives it gives the um
like our mono cropping and being like
okay soy is being planted here and then
we can we can
get away with with making a lot of
calories with very little labor
but a lot of energy and it costs us our
planet and our
health permaculture helps us create
food in very little land well taking
care of the soil there's very little
labor involved right it's just like
planted it takes care of itself and you
go out and pick it and we could
with an app have all of that information
i mean you can find out what your soil
is
you can grow it you can create the seeds
and you can have a marketplace of
sharing the seeds and
like for me the idea of losing packaged
foods sounds like hell because it's how
i feed me and my kid
with my executive dysfunction and just
needing that that you know those two
bucks
for expensive mac and cheese and yet
every time i open it i'm like this is a
cup of
dried pasta and a package of cheese
sauce why can't i
just get a cup of pasta and bulk cheese
sauce and you know what i mean like
three tablespoons
and we have granola bars why can't we
like figure out how to put them
in a reusable package and get it like we
could have manufactured food or
convenience of food on a more localized
scale
that i would be willing to go and
volunteer and put my time in to get my
contribution out
but i but like i can't i'm not making
our granola bars you know what i mean
like
i can't like make that amount of food um
that my kid would eat that i would eat
that would be there for convenience
and but to do it on a more collective
basis i could
i couldn't do it with my neighbors i can
do it with my community of
putting in the labor sharing in the cost
of food and getting that information out
but still sorry sorry going on oh i was
just going to say that
you know still with 10 000 people and
100 000
that's like i mean in my eyes that's
kind of like
spitting on a forest fire it's like
against
monsanto i mean there's lots of
solutions we can utilize
to to you know create
you know food security for ourselves and
we've already mentioned a number of
those
which could solve the problems but again
unless you
remove monsanto and all of the other
you know for-profit companies that are
you know
in that same realm how do you
i i mean um yeah how do you get monsanto
to back down
and i and this is because monsanto's
evil they're evil incarnate and they
like we'll sue people
with buy a monster even grow their own
their own food right like
seeds blew over onto your field you
didn't even want them there if anything
you should be able to sue monsanto and
monsanto ends up suing you
just having a map of those instances
having a map of ooh these people use
monsanto and these people
like using google maps and having that
just be very very clear about yeah what
just
so happens these 17 people around them
are growing monsanto
yeah they didn't they didn't actually
grow it themselves and just keeping
track
of who who actually um
who they're suing and why they're suing
them and
the key to the food industry this idea
that it's lower class and it's also
um doesn't pay well and yet it's the
only
thing that matters right it's about to
be like gold
grain is where it's you know what i mean
like that's gonna be like
gold doesn't matter when you're starving
and yet we all could if we have even a
little patch of land grow
grow food but what does it take it takes
good soil it takes sunlight it takes
water
and it takes some kind of knowledge of
the food and seeds and
and that kind of information we can
share in and if we concentrate on
over monsanto
yeah 10 000 people might not i don't
think that would be our best use of time
is
is is trying to dismantle monsanto even
though i do think they're evil
i think having 10 000 people in
vancouver
could create a local vegan meal delivery
service
that gets people delicious food for way
less because you're
almost your entire neighborhood is
getting it right so you know you can get
this meal delivered on mondays and this
meal delivered on tuesdays
and have it in reusable packages because
we want it to be in reusable packages
now i think there's a i mean i don't
know the solution to monsanto
but again using the uh going along with
the star wars theme that i've been on
is uh there's gotta be some
way in to kind of get
into the heart of the death star and you
know
make the whole thing collapse and that
there's got to be
some weak point you know there's tons
we just have to like right now it's not
like taking on the big monsanto giants
is like
that's not as effective as coming up
with solutions that actually draw people
in right no one's picking monsanto when
they have their local cooperative where
they can you don't even give four hours
a month and get
get a discount on food and do like if
you give something something better
they're not going to support monsanto
and what i've decided is like the cure
for war that we could like actually
track
ceos and boycott them to the nth degree
say no your kids can't go to our schools
you can't come and eat at our
restaurants
you don't get to exist when you're
creating landmines like economically you
don't exist we're not giving you money
we're not letting you use our services
it's not happening
monsanto's in that category like i'm not
okay with boycotting people
individual level except when they're
evil and monsanto is evil so if you're
gonna be a ceo a cfo of monsanto
yeah find a new job or you're gonna get
boycotted yeah
but but i don't think there's enough
people there's no way there's been
right now michelin restaurants are
boycotting these guys you know what i
mean
this is their bread and butter there's
no way which is yes now but things
they care about no boycott well you
absolutely can i mean you can cancel
people with
a thousand twitter like a thousand
twitter people going off on them
let alone not four seasons hotels you
can't though i mean
they could they they can still have the
sweet four seasons
yeah but they're in bed then you start
going down the line now you start
boycotting four seasons
[Laughter]
yeah but given the the current climate
we live in with big tech
censoring so much and essentially you
know
big tech you know monsanto and everybody
has
the hands in the back pocket of big tech
to use them
at their disposal i mean your boycott
won't even
show up on the radar for people because
it'll just be censored
you're absolutely yeah so which is why i
wouldn't say that
fool's errands trying to take on
something like monsanto i think
well i'll sign up for the monsanto
strike force i'll be yes
i mean you know and it's not like i mean
even if you were able to overcome the
security and whatever it's not like all
of monsanto is in one place right
you know that's it it's somewhat
distributed they have
offices and centers and distribution
centers and factories and research labs
and blah blah blah all over the
shop so
you know it's it's the only way the only
way really is to just
do your own thing that doesn't require
anything that they do
and you know attract more and more
people into doing that thing and
every single person that starts doing
their own thing is is one less little
bit of power that monsanto has i mean
that's
it is the only way i know it doesn't
sound as sexy as going and blowing up
the monsanto center or whatever
oh no i'm not suggesting that but if you
if you if you demolish their stock price
they will lose a lot of power and that's
why i think
you know a market collapse
total market collapse would be
the it would be a godsend for a lot of
what we're trying to accomplish because
it would just bring it not only would it
bring big tech but it would bring
monsanto and all of these evil corpse to
their knees
maybe yes um and in a way i share your
desire for that but
also there would be a huge amount of
chaos calls but the other thing is as
well that just because
the stock market collapses right that
doesn't mean that
those research labs and distribution
centers and so on and so on and so on
don't still exist
and so you know it's it's it's only the
legal fiction
which has gone away and i'm sure they
have security firms and lots of guns and
blah blah blah blah blah you know
and i'm sure they've thought about this
and have prepared for this eventuality
right and have and have
plans in place far better ones and far
more
actualized than than than we do so yeah
that necessarily gets rid of them is my
point it may actually just increase
their grip
because it's such chaos then they're the
only ones that are still organized you
know
but i mean you know to be able to get
loans and
and pay employees and you know operate
from their capitalist um
modality they need
the stock that i mean their stock is
their funding mechanism
so i mean if you take out if you if you
severely diminish their
their method of funding uh that
that will help that will help and i
think
yeah anyway that that's a much larger
topic
that's like bringing down the stock
market so they don't have a way of um
of making money and then they they stop
being monsanto even if they still have
even if they could still have a lab and
and and whatnot um isn't all
they're highly leveraged and then they
won't be able to make their debt
payments and then they have to
severely cut back their workforce and
their research budgets
and everything just has to be hugely
scaled back so that would be
that would be very very bad for them um
but the thing is
like doing that also takes away the
indep like our stock price
on our stock price and it's not really
the equivalent but our incomes right our
incomes go down as people lose their
jobs as people have all these things
happen
whereas if we concentrate on the other
side of it which is like how do i feed
myself without monsanto
how do i feed myself with less and less
reliance on manufactured
nestle products um which were probably
all owned by nestle even though they're
an even though they used to not be they
used to be organic and good and they
still are but they're under that guys
because they could see it that there was
profit in it
and to be able to work like
there's this math that i'm sure i do and
a lot of people do in their head like
okay if i make twenty dollars an hour
why would i grow my own food when it
costs exit right like
like i grew my own tomatoes and they
were little cherry tomatoes and i was
like oh
i like cherry tomatoes but this entire
plant gave me one box of them so
looking after it all year gave me the
equivalent of five dollars worth
that's 15 minutes i put more than 15
minutes into this like but whereas
i have cherry tomatoes i can still eat
them like removing the math of did my
labor
how much of my labor was here and just
hey ten thousand of us
working together putting in money would
be more than a hundred thousand putting
in money for a 3d farm putting in money
for just to putting in our labor on
farms that already exist and are just
going to destroy their food
and like how do we collectively figure
out how
my meal gets made not just how do i grow
my own food because
it's going to go to waste if i have to
cook it into food
whereas like together we can create how
do we feed ourselves and remove
instead of okay we have to pay people 20
bucks to be in the field
all of the vault all of the time and
labor and resources it takes to get us
fed can we distribute that amongst
ourselves and anyone can come in and do
that any you know it doesn't matter if
you're rich or poor
it costs you 10 hours a week to get your
food delivered to get
all of your meals delivered ten i don't
know how much hours that would actually
be
but ten hours who you don't need
everyone to do that you would need 10
000 people locally to do that
and to figure out you wouldn't
necessarily give them 100 of their food
but it starts at 10 and grows and grows
and grows it's maybe
a meal their evening meal
and then and then figuring out reverse
but it's like dealing with the
individuals and finding out where do you
get your food and how could you get your
food and when you
teach people and allow people to grow
their own food they already have that
resilience because they're
especially when they're working together
having your own farm and growing your
own food is powerful but doing it with
your neighbor so you know if you're in
drought someone a
drought would be hard but if yours your
stuff doesn't has a micro
climate that makes it not work and
someone else's does there's enough food
to go around if your whole place has a
drought
one of the other local places doesn't
and they know that
you know it's not monsanto we're not
relying on the charity
or horrible business practice of
monsanto we can create systems that are
come participate and you get it we don't
have to pay you
and pay out wages and pay that stuff
it's about like utilizing
our volunteer hours utilizing the sun
utilizing the soil and making it
healthier
it just had a thought and this is
completely off topic but
real quick um what if we do
a solution raising some time and the
the purpose of the solution raising
would be to find
solutions on how to even acquire
ten thousand people and a hundred
thousand dollars because without that
all of the solutions that we think of
for these topics
you know that then if if we have that
kind of bolted down
uh it might be interesting because we
could actually kind of push through
some of these uh ideas we're talking
about
anyway yeah there's um we'd actually it
was the one thing we somewhat failed at
we had a switch and raising on solution
raising and we've come up with powerful
solutions for prisons and everything
else but the solution raising on
solution raising
it was a little bit it just didn't we
didn't come up with anything necessarily
but my brain has so i am creating a
meta-learning magic which will get us to
10 000 people put
in 25 a month which will get us
resources and it just started yesterday
with our the first day of our six-week
course so there is stuff in the
in the pipelines and after the six week
course there will be more six week
courses that will be offered to more
people and more people
and exponential growth and it will yes
because we come with powerful solutions
but if they can't go anywhere there
isn't a way to get 10 000 people
together
what the f is the point um do you mind
do you mind sending me some
just shoot me an email with some info on
that i'd love to check it out
sure yeah i have a few unlisted videos i
can i can i can send you
you can see the progression because yeah
it's awesome it's not
as with me it's like it's somewhat
chaotic where it keeps changing which is
why even at the sixth week when i'm
finally introducing
everyone in the six week course has
already been introduced to the idea
but the idea but it'll change by the
time we get to the sixth week when i
actually finally introduce it
like this is what you're signing on
board for where you want to sign on
board for it
and so just keep where whatever you
think it's also going to be changing
cool sounds good what does your shirt
say eric i think you're wearing that
last time and i was like
something debt something debt equals
slavery
money equals debt debt equals slavery
liberate mankind.com oh it's like you
got your own shirt made
i did it
so let me ask you let me ask you guys a
question yeah
how does all of this change in your mind
if and i know this is a big if i'm just
asking you to suspend this belief just
for a moment right
um if you believe like the really far
out there version like
in most narratives that go on in the
media right there's the sort of there's
the official line here and there's the
way out there conspiracy thing here and
i'm normally somewhere around about
here-ish something like that right
now if it was let's say that this is
true right that for
centuries millennia whatever there has
been this very small group of people who
have manipulated the affairs of man to
further their own
power and influence and luxury and and
you know grown the population
and figured out more and more
sophisticated ways of enslaving
populations without them even knowing
that they're enslaved
um and that there is the point has now
been reached where human beings are no
longer the most valuable resources on
this planet and there is a cult
there is a cull going on and so all of
this thing we're seeing in collapse of
food chains
destruction of soil destruction of a
natural environment is not
faults of the syst this is not
externalities ejected by the system but
the actual purpose of the system right
this is the goal
how does that change these conversations
that we have for you
if that were the case it doesn't it
doesn't i mean i'm a kind of already
under the premise of both like it's just
chaotic it's just
the opposite of beloved malignant
neglect that it's just the
the like externalities of people working
on their own self-interest
yeah kind of i kind of i kind of think
that too but i'm just saying if it is
even if it is either way they may want
to kill me they may want to kill other
people it's part of why we're
distributing it right it doesn't need to
it's not one leader it's not one
one piece of technology it's not you
can't take out
one one pillar and have it crumble it
needs to be resilient it needs to be
something of like yes and even if this
person dies
everything continues and part of what
the mlm that we're creating is doing um
is it doesn't rely on facebook and
youtube's algorithm
right because i mean i don't actually
think they've grey blocked me i don't
actually think i'm important enough i
just think i kind of suck at youtube
my point my point is though jubilee if
you're let's assume you're mlm you like
is incredibly successful right in six
months from now you've got 10 000 people
and lots of things going on and blah
blah blah blah blah and it's
and it's still growing exponentially
right and in six months you're going to
have a million and six months later
you're going to have 100 million right
yep as soon as you become an actual
threat
that's what i'm saying the difference
the difference between it being
externalities that have gone wrong and
it being deliberate is that if you
create something that does actually
start to really solve problems
you are now a threat to this thing and
now they just come and boss you off
right you get you know
dragged off the guantanamo or two in the
back of the head or whatever it might be
yeah no i was always making this with
the idea that that is absolutely what is
going to happen i will be murdered for
this
and it doesn't matter because all of my
is out there and because of how
we're growing
right it's not every one of the rest of
the 10 000 if necessary
as well i mean right they would have to
find all of them and kill
right and killing five people is hard
enough killing ten thousand people isn't
even with
all like it's they can't do that they
just can't now
and if they do that's ten thousand
people distributed all over the world
are like wait they were all into the
same thing
that might happen in which case we're
does humanity and wife try
like if they can if they will succeed at
stopping us no matter what
right that's not a guarantee even if
that is the case so i'm actually
i'm actually hugely into
i don't know if you you guys have heard
of the concept of
daos decentralized autonomous
organizations
um and actually jubilee you you spoke
with
matan field from daostak
and he's that over at dalstack they're
kind of building a governance
system uh to create um
daos and um
i i think that that solves
this issue and and the issue is
we all form a dao and the dao could be
you know comprised of 10 a hundred
thousand
a million people the dao has control
over
a trust with millions of dollars in it
and
from a distributed decentralized
anonymous
way that you can't shut down because of
cryptography
um that enables
us to form an organization
on the blockchain to you know come up
with solutions
distribute capital to those that need it
that need it
vote on things without a third party
coming in and things up um
this solves so many of of
of these these issues that we're
discussing i mean you
you kill one of us and there's you know
10 000 others
with a distributed you know distributed
organization
which isn't housed by some legal entity
within a nation state that you can just
sue
you know that
that's what i see as our kind of saving
grace in
in this whole thing
it requires the internet sure but you
know
if we don't have the internet we've got
much bigger problems on our hand
here so hopefully we can keep that
running and hopefully
you know i mean if people start losing
access to the internet
uh you know hopefully there's backup
systems or
or whatever but yeah in the streets for
sure
then they also lose a lot of power as
well so i think the internet
is kind of a a commons which if i'm then
i feel if i'm them i've already built my
own second internet right for the day
that we need to shut this internet down
because we can't control it anymore
yeah and that's part of creating dot
like is creating something i mean
holochain has their own
their own internet and their own and i
don't rely on either dow stack or
holochain because neither of them have
actually
like done the thing that they're like
they don't exist yet so it's kind of
just
creative cool projects that need each
other
but there's that that's the technology
piece which i do think is coming down
the line
there's well i think matan was talking
about uh
commons uh he was talking to you about
commons and i think they're very close
to launching the commons app which
essentially will be
an iphone app where you could go and
create your own dao that that's called
you know jubilee
saves the world and you know
we we could all vote on proposals on
what to do
we could all you know donate money it's
kind of similar to this
you know mlm type type thing but
you know in kind of a more updated way
but
yeah i mean yeah the the i when i talk
to a lot of people they they always
bring up you know well what if the
internet goes down
i i really can't argue with that but
but assuming it doesn't go down
these these technologies are very very
very close
to to being ready for the mainstream so
yeah i would just i would i would
consider those and look into them yeah
no i i just i
every like people are creating things
relying on the dial stack being they're
relying on holochain being there and i'm
like well what if it's not
like great project but if dallas staff
doesn't happen can you still exist right
you still need the local self-sustaining
resilient community
i mean that's yeah all right so we are
at the hour
i would like to do what we normally do
which is go back to our topic
and uh resiliency what is the most
powerful thing you think we could do
with ten thousand people and a hundred
thousand dollars
to help with food sovereignty in our
lives in the world
that could could potentially take place
if we did have those ten thousand people
who are willing to put in 10 dollars
i don't know how much it would cost to
build a small vertical farm
in a town or a city somewhere but if you
could get 10 000 people in the same city
100 000 i dare so you could build at
least a small one right and this could
be
more of a symbol than anything else
right look look at this thing right
so cool it takes up a few square
meters and it produces x amount of
whatever
you know every month or every year or
whatever you know if we had
50 of these in the city that's it we
wouldn't need to ship any vegetables in
you know we can grow what we want year
round
and i mean with an indoor environment
you can grow things like strawberries
and lemons and
well lemons is a bad example because
that's trees but you know the baby you
can grow sort of subtropical kind of
stuff
even in even in temperate zones so yeah
i like that i like that i think that's
roughly in the sort of scale
my vote would be to create a a food
security dao
and then the members of that dao uh
that have pooled the capital together
would then vote
on proposals to create these types of
indoor vertical farming solutions and
then
and then the dao would then be the
organization
to then go out and fulfill solutions
like that that that would that would be
my vote
i would like um 10 000 people in
vancouver to get together
and create a local vegan delivery
service that was delicious and cheap
that
didn't have all the waste that all the
other ones do um because that would help
me the most
in my life i don't need i'm not vegan
but i feel like vegan is more
more universal and more you could have
one meal that works for more
for more people and and um ten thousand
people could get that down to five
dollars per
per serving which would be amazing
especially for shared in that labor
sharing and the cooking and the delivery
and all of that stuff it would just help
me the most and globally i think the
most powerful thing would be
information on how to grow food together
how to kind of without the dow stack of
what you're
like how to actually create a 3d farm
how to
how to how to do those things and how to
actually bring in the people
who want to do that so if you have an
idea for a project like a 3d form that
you can bring in those people much more
more easily for the people that are low
risk and can see
eight months out a year out and don't
want to compete with game a people who
are like well we're fine there's food in
the supermarket we're not going to
starve
that's give it two weeks that food won't
be there if the truck stopped coming
um yeah thank you for joining me for the
solution raising on food security thank
you eric for coming up with the topic
because i didn't read before this and
next week we'll talk about refugees
and goodbye youtube
nope nope every time every time i go to